90. Danger in the Sea It was the worst environmental disaster in
American history. Here's how the BP, British Petroleum Oil Spill, and the Gulf of Mexico
on April 20, 2010 happened. 1. The government wasn't watching. Wouldn't
it be great if you could make up the rules for every game you played? That's basically
what BP was allowed to do. The US government generally let BP regulate itself. No one was
around to tell the company no or force it to maintain safety standards. 2. The offshore
oil rig involved in the spill was sealing the well it had drilled. Workers tested the
seal once but didn't do any other more expensive safety tests to be absolutely sure the seal
3. As we later learned, the cement used for the well was not allowed enough time to set. BP knew
this but believed it could be strengthened later. 4. A gas bubble escaped from the badly sealed
well. The gas rose through the pipe and reached the air at the oil rig where it exploded. 11
workers were killed, the rig burned and slowly sank. 5. A blowout preventer should have come
on to seal the well automatically. It didn't. The well pipe had been knocked out of place by the
explosion. That kept the blowout preventer from sealing the well as it should have. 6. BP,
rushing to fix the well, accidentally opened a bigger hole and the oil started gushing. By
some estimates, 205.8 million gallons spilled into the Gulf in 87 days. However, a judge later
ruled that BP was only responsible for about 130 million gallons. Livelihoods were destroyed,
countless animals and plants were killed. The effects of the oil on the surface and floor of
the ocean will continue for decades. A study presented in April 2017 showed that the oil
spill had caused 17.2 billion US dollars in damage to the Gulf of Mexico's natural resources.